{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "As a child, this man spoke the South Carolina creole language Gullah. In 1991, this man was\nat the center of widely viewed Congressional hearings over his alleged use of a can of Coca-Cola\nto sexually harass Anita Hill. He has since been accused of rarely speaking and visibly falling\nasleep during oral arguments. For 10 points, name this conservative Supreme Court Justice.",
      "answer": [
        "Clarence Thomas",
        "Thomas"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This character is portrayed in the 2008 conservative satire film An American Carol by Kelsey\nGrammer. Kirk Douglas portrayed him in Is Paris Burning?, and his \"last days\" were the subject\nof a 1986 TV movie in which his most notable portrayer reprised this role. For 10 points, name\nthis commander of the Third Army who was played in a 1970 biopic by George C. Scott.",
      "answer": [
        "George Smith Patton",
        "Patton"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An opera from this country is about a peasant who averts an invasion by leading the Polish\narmy into a forest. This country's nationalist group \"The Mighty Handful\" composed Pictures at\nan Exhibition and Flight of the Bumblebee. For 10 points, name this home country of Modest\nMussorgky (pr. moo-SORG-skee) and Rimsky-Korsakov (pr. RIM-skee-CORE-suh-koff).",
      "answer": "Russia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Charles Redheffer's exhibition of one of these devices was undone by a precocious child who\nnoticed the wearing of gear teeth. John Gamgee's attempt to create a device of this kind called\nthe Zeromotor failed because of the energy needed to cool ammonia. For 10 points, name these\npseudoscientific devices which were proved impossible by the Second Law of Thermodynamics.",
      "answer": [
        "perpetual motion machines",
        "perpetual motion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was a planned stunt orchestrated by George Rappelyea and other local business\nleaders, who correctly predicted that celebrities such as H.L. Mencken, William Jennings Bryan,\nand Clarence Darrow would flock to Dayton, Tennessee and bring tourist dollars with them. For\n10 points, name this 1925 proceeding over the charge of \"teaching evolution.\"",
      "answer": [
        "Scopes trial",
        "Scopes",
        "monkey trial",
        "monkey"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The William was scuttled by a storm before being subject to this event, which instead targeted\nthe Eleanor, Beaver, and Dartmouth. It began on the saying of the code phrase \"This meeting\ncan do nothing further to save the country\" by Samuel Adams. For 10 points, name this 1773\nincident in which the Sons of Liberty dressed as Mohawks and destroyed British goods.",
      "answer": "Boston Tea Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "The introduction of copper plating caused incidents of this kind named for Spithead and Nore.\nFletcher Christian led another event of this kind, which caused a new population to settle on\nPitcairn Island and opposed William Bligh. For 10 points, name these events in British history in\nwhich the crew of a ship rebelled against the captain, as on the HMS Bounty.",
      "answer": "mutiny"
    },
    {
      "question": "This position was first held by a man named St. Augustine who is not to be confused with the\none who wrote The City of God. This position is currently held by Justin Welby, who succeeded\nRowan Williams. For 10 points, name this religious position at the head of the Anglican Church,\nwhich is named for the city that was the destination of Chaucer’s pilgrims.",
      "answer": "Archbishop of Canterbury"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man worked under the non-painter Diego Velázquez, who dispatched him from Cuba.\nThis man's forces were nearly routed in La Noche Triste (pr. NOH-chay TREES-tay), and he\nwas aided by the traitor La Malinche (pr. mah-LEEN-chay). For 10 points, name this conqueror\nof Tenochtitlan (pr. tay-NOK-teet-lon) who defeated Montezuma to claim Mexico for Spain.",
      "answer": [
        "Hernan Cortes",
        "Cortes"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This military leader was declared a martyr by Pope Callixtus III, a generation after this saint's\ncapture at Compiègne (pr. cahmp-YEN-yuh). Pierre Cauchon (pr. COO-shun) led the court\nwhich condemned her to be burned at the stake in 1431 following her relief of the siege of\nOrléans (pr. OH-lee-ahn). For 10 points, name this teenage French patriot of the Hundred Years\nWar.",
      "answer": [
        "Joan of Arc",
        "Jeanne d'Arc"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The \"July Theses\" defined the Communist regime of what Eastern European country,\nwhose Ploiești (pr. ploy-ESH-tuh) oil fields were targeted by Operation Tidal Wave?",
      "answer": "Romania"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Biologist George Gaylord Simpson was a vehement opponent of this theory. Frank Taylor first\nproposed this theory in 1908, based on observing similarities in distant mountain ranges. This\ntheory was picked up in 1912 by Alfred Wegener, who popularized it. For 10 points, identify this\ntheory, ancestral to plate tectonics, which states that large land masses move over time.",
        "answer": "continental drift"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wegener proposed that the continents could be fit together to form an \"Urkontinent,\" a\nprehistoric land mass now known by what Greek-derived name?",
        "answer": "Pangaea"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The planned city of Fatehpur Sikri (pr. FAH-tay-poor SEE-kree) was built as a capital in\nwhat is now this country. Several ancient empires in this present-day country were ruled from\nPataliputra (pr. puh-TAH-lee-POO-truh). Edwin Lutyens designed this country's current\ncapital across the Jammu River from the Red Fort. For 10 points, name this country governed\nfrom New Delhi.",
        "answer": [
          "India",
          "Republic of India",
          "Bharat"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another planned city, Le Corbusier's (pr. core-BOO-see-eyz) city of Chandigarh (pr.\nCHAHN-dee-gar), is the capital of what \"five-river\" region of north India, the center of\nSikhism?",
        "answer": "Punjab"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In protest of this war, the \"Spot Resolutions\" were introduced by then-Congressman Abraham\nLincoln. Another opponent of this war spent a night in jail after refusing to pay a poll tax that\nwent to fund it. This war was stridently opposed by Henry David Thoreau and other\ntranscendentalists as an extension of the slave power. For 10 points, name this war in which the\nbattles of Veracruz, Cerro Gordo, and Chapultepec were fought against Santa Anna.",
        "answer": [
          "Mexican-American War",
          "Mexican"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which intercepted communication helped trigger American entry into World War I\nafter it suggested that Mexico could recover territory lost in the Mexican American War?",
        "answer": [
          "Zimmerman Note",
          "Zimmerman Telegram"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This team’s best defensive player of the 1970s missed the entire 1979 season in favor of\nprofessional boxing. This team, which employed Ed “Too Tall” Jones, defeated the Dolphins and\nBroncos to win two 1970s Super Bowls, and lost two more appearances, both to the Steelers. For\n10 points, name this team of quarterback Roger Staubach and coach Tom Landry.",
        "answer": [
          "Dallas Cowboys",
          "Dallas",
          "Cowboys"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Who was the quarterback for all three of the Cowboys 1990s Super Bowl wins?",
        "answer": [
          "Troy Aikman",
          "Aikman"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man won his first senate race over Robert La Follete Jr. He was challenged by Army\ncounsel Joseph Welch during hearings where Roy Cohn assisted him. In a speech to the\nRepublican Women's Club of Wheeling, West Virginia, he presented a list of names. For 10\npoints, name this Wisconsin Senator who instigated the early 1950s \"Red Scare\" in his hunt for\nCommunists.",
        "answer": [
          "Joseph McCarthy",
          "McCarthy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "McCarthy originally was looking for Communists in what federal agency, which was\nled at the time by Dean Acheson?",
        "answer": [
          "Department of State",
          "State"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The man who won the 1970 election for this office was opposed in a coup known as the\n\"Tanquetazo\" (pr. ton-kay-TOT-zoh) and finally overthrown after nationalizing the copper\nindustry, with the approval of Henry Kissinger and Richard Nixon. For 10 points, identify this\noffice which Salvador Allende (pr. eye-EN-day) lost in a military coup led by Augusto Pinochet\n(pr. pee-noh-CHAY).",
        "answer": "President of Chile"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which other South American political office did Dilma Rousseff win reelection to in\n2014?",
        "answer": "President of Brazil"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This religion opposed the Nestorian heresy at the Council of Ephesus (pr. EFF-uh-sis) and\nadvanced the doctrine of \"hypostasis\" (pr. high-PAH-stuh-sis) at the Council of Chalcedon.\nEarlier, this religion challenged the Arian movement at the Council of Nicaea (pr. nigh-SEEuh). For 10 points, name this religion whose early ecumenical councils met under the\nsupervision of the Pope.",
        "answer": [
          "Christianity",
          "Christian",
          "Roman Catholicism",
          "Catholic",
          "Catholicism",
          "Eastern Orthodoxy",
          "Orthodox"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What early Christian martyr is usually said to have been killed for refusing to submit to\nEmperor Claudius II on February 14 of the year 269?",
        "answer": [
          "Saint Valentine",
          "Valentine"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This goddess, who was born from the left eye of Izanagi (pr. ee-zuh-NAH-gee), is\nworshipped at a \"grand shrine\" that is torn down and rebuilt every twenty years. She is believed\nto be the ancestor of the \"tenno,\" who sits on the Chrysanthemum Throne. For 10 points, name\nthis sun goddess, the sister of Susanowo, and the patroness of the Imperial house of Japan.",
        "answer": "Amaterasu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Japanese emperor formally renounced his divine status in the \"Jewel Voice\nBroadcast\" of 1945?",
        "answer": [
          "Hirohito",
          "Showa"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "VICTORIAN SOCIETY",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Author of A Christmas Carol and Great Expectations who complained about social\nconditions?",
          "answer": [
            "Charles Dickens",
            "Dickens"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Long-term economic phenomenon in which mechanized factories became the dominant sector\nof the economy?",
          "answer": "Industrial Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Serial killer who targeted prostitutes in London in 1888?",
          "answer": "Jack the Ripper"
        },
        {
          "question": "Major British possession in Asia, which Victoria was declared Empress of?",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that was the world’s most populous throughout Victoria’s reign?",
          "answer": "London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conservative Party leader whom Victoria favored over his rival Gladstone?",
          "answer": [
            "Benjamin Disraeli",
            "Disraeli"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Playwright and author of The Picture of Dorian Grey who was sentenced to jail for his\nsexuality?",
          "answer": [
            "Oscar Wilde",
            "Wilde"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Famous Crimean War era poem written by Tennyson about a disastrous cavalry mission?",
          "answer": "The Charge of the Light Brigade"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In England during the time of Queen Victoria, who or what was the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "AMERICAN COLONIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Under the name “New Netherland” by Dutch settlers?",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "When Lord Baltimore wished to establish a colony tolerating Catholics?",
          "answer": "Maryland"
        },
        {
          "question": "As a Spanish colony surrounding the fort at St. Augustine?",
          "answer": "Florida"
        },
        {
          "question": "As a debtors’ haven by James Oglethorpe?",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "When the Jamestown settlement was defended by John Smith?",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "After Roger Williams established religious toleration?",
          "answer": "Rhode Island"
        },
        {
          "question": "By Ethan Allen’s “Green Mountain Boys” revolt?",
          "answer": "Vermont"
        },
        {
          "question": "By the followers of dissident Puritan Thomas Hooker?",
          "answer": "Connecticut"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "What present-day state of the United States was founded..."
    },
    {
      "category": "THE SPANISH ARMADA",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Sent off in what historic year?",
          "answer": "1588"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attempting to return England to what religion?",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Catholicism",
            "Catholic",
            "Catholicism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sent against what Queen of England?",
          "answer": "Elizabeth I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Funded in part by Spanish conquests over what Native Americans of the Andes Mountains?",
          "answer": [
            "Incans",
            "Inca",
            "Incas",
            "Incan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Initially combatted by what commander of the Golden Hind?",
          "answer": [
            "Francis Drake",
            "Drake"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Shattered near the Munster and Connacht (pr. cuh-NOKT) areas of what island when it was\nblown off course on its return?",
          "answer": "Ireland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organized by what Spanish king?",
          "answer": "Philip II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unsuccessfully commanded by what Spanish military officer?",
          "answer": [
            "Duke of Medina Sidonia",
            "Medina Sidonia",
            "Don Alonso Perez de Guzman y de Zuniga-Sotomayor",
            "Guzman"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "The Spanish Armada was..."
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This company made the \"Kingsbury Commitment\" in 1913, agreeing to sell off its stake\nin Western Union. In 1984, this company again was brought up on (20 pts) ",
        "antitrust charges,\nresulting in its fracturing into seven \"Baby (10 pts) ",
        "Bells.\" For 10 points, name this company\nwhich formerly held a monopoly on U.S. telephone service and now is the second-largest\nwireless carrier."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "AT&T Corporation",
        "AT&T",
        "American Telephone and Telegraph"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Fossils of this species were first found in the Engis Caves of Belgium, though they get\ntheir name from subsequent finds on the outskirts of Dusseldorf in a namesake (20 pts) ",
        "valley.\nThis species was once believed to have been rendered extinct by bands of rock-throwing\npredators, though it is now known from DNA markers that they (10 pts) ",
        "interbred with the\nancestors of modern humans. For 10 points, name this large-skulled hominid which survived in\nEurope until 40,000 BC."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Neanderthals",
        "Neanderthal"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was originally supposed to be the candidate of the Union Party in the 1936\nPresidential election. After his death, his brother (20 pts) ",
        "Earl served three more terms on his\nplatform. This politician proposed confiscating fortunes beyond a million dollars as part of\nhis \"Share the Wealth\" plan, which he promoted with the slogan (10 pts) ",
        "\"Every Man a King.\"\nFor 10 points, name this \"Kingfish\" who was assassinated by Carl Weiss in 1935, ending his\niron-fisted rule over Louisiana."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Huey Long",
        "Long"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Central Asian conquerors known as the Hepthalites are also called the \"white\"\nversion of these people, who may also be identical to the Chinese (20 pts) ",
        "Xiongnu (pr. shongNOO). These people advanced into Western Europe shortly after the death of Bleda, and in\n452, Pope Leo I negotiated a retreat of their forces from Rome. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, name these\nconquerors who briefly dominated Eastern Europe under the leadership of Attila."
      ],
      "answer": "Huns"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Tony Pastor and E.F. Albee were major producers of this form of entertainment. Ethnic\nversions of this entertainment genre included the Jewish \"Borscht Belt\" and the black\n\"Chitlin (20 pts) ",
        "Circuit.\" This genre strictly prohibited anything offensive to \"family\"\nsensibilities and originally played many of the theaters that were later converted to\nshowing movies. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, identify this most popular form of entertainment in pre-1920\nAmerica, consisting of a series of stage acts."
      ],
      "answer": "Vaudeville"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this larger operation, soldiers were executed at Chenogne (pr. chay-NON) in\nrevenge for the earlier Malmedy (pr. mahl-may-DEE) Massacre. Anthony McAuliffe issued\nthe singular reply (20 pts) ",
        "\"Nuts!\" to a surrender demand during this operation, which was\nnamed for the (10 pts) ",
        "shape created in a map of troop lines in the Ardennes forest. For 10 points,\nname this late 1944 World War II initiative, the final major German offensive of the war."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of the Bulge",
        "Bulge"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This organization set up a front called the Fairfield Foundation, through which it\npromoted what Nelson Rockefeller dubbed \"free enterprise painting.\" In response to\nHarry Truman's derision of modern art in 1947, this organization attempted to (20 pts) ",
        "finance\nmovements such as abstract expressionism in order to promote American cultural vitality\nagainst the stagnant (10 pts) ",
        "socialist realism of the USSR. For 10 points, name this external spy\nagency of the United States."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "CIA",
        "Central Intelligence Agency"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Elbert Hubbard's inspirational story A Message to Garcia is set during this war. Mark\nTwain became a leader of the Anti-Imperialist League, which opposed this war. During this\nwar, Frederic (20 pts) ",
        "Remington worked as a photographer for William Randolph (10 pts) ",
        "Hearst,\nwho promised \"I'll furnish the war\" through his \"yellow journalism\" outlet, the New York\nJournal. For 10 points, name this war in which Cuba achieved independence and the U.S.\nannexed Puerto Rico."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Spanish-American War",
        "Spanish-American"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) A major terrorist group in this country absorbed the Socialist Patients' Collective, a group\nwhich believes that people with illnesses were the oppressed class in capitalist societies, and\nlaunched a 1977 campaign known as its \"autumn.\" This home of the (20 pts) ",
        "Red Army Faction\nwas also where members of (10 pts) ",
        "Black September targeted athletes in 1972. For 10 points, name\nthis country where terrorist incidents included the attack on Israelis at the Munich Olympics."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "West Germany",
        "Germany"
      ]
    }
  ]
}